<?xml version='1.0'?> <!--*-nxml-*-->
<!DOCTYPE refentry PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
        "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd">

<refentry id="bus1">

  <refentryinfo>
    <title>bus1</title>
    <productname>bus1</productname>

    <authorgroup>
      <author>
        <contrib>Documentation</contrib>
        <firstname>David</firstname>
        <surname>Herrmann</surname>
      </author>
      <author>
        <contrib>Documentation</contrib>
        <firstname>Tom</firstname>
        <surname>Gundersen</surname>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>
  </refentryinfo>

  <refmeta>
    <refentrytitle>bus1</refentrytitle>
    <manvolnum>7</manvolnum>
  </refmeta>

  <refnamediv>
    <refname>bus1</refname>
    <refpurpose>Kernel Message Bus</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>

  <refsynopsisdiv>
    <funcsynopsis>
      <funcsynopsisinfo>#include &lt;linux/bus1.h&gt;</funcsynopsisinfo>
    </funcsynopsis>
  </refsynopsisdiv>

  <refsect1> <!-- DESCRIPTION -->
    <title>Description</title>
    <para>
The bus1 Kernel Message Bus defines and implements a distributed object model.
It allows local processes to send messages to objects owned by remote processes,
as well as share their own objects with others. Object ownership is static and
cannot be transferred. Access to remote objects is prohibited, unless it was
explicitly granted. Processes can transmit messages to a remote object via the
message bus, transferring a data payload, object access rights, or file
descriptors.
    </para>
    <para>
To participate on the message bus, a peer context must be created. Peer contexts
are kernel objects, identified by a file descriptor. They are not bound to any
process, but can be shared freely. The peer context provides a message queue to
store all incoming messages, a registry for all locally owned objects, and
tracks access rights to remote objects. A peer context never serves as
routing entity, but merely as anchor for peer-owned resources. Any message on
the bus is always destined for an object, and the bus takes care to transfer a
message into the message queue of the peer context that owns this object.
    </para>
    <para>
The message bus manages object access using capabilities. That is, by default
only the owner of an object is granted access rights. No other peer can access
the object, nor are they aware of the existence of the object. However, access
rights can be transmitted as auxiliary data with any message, effectively
granting them to the receiver of the message. This also works transitively, that
is, any peer that was granted access to an object can pass on those rights, even
if they do not own the object. But mind that no access rights can ever be
revoked, besides the owner destroying the object.
    </para>

    <refsect2>
      <title>Nodes and Handles</title>
      <para>
Each peer context comes with a registry of owned objects, which in bus1
parlance are called <emphasis>nodes</emphasis>. A peer is always the exclusive
owner of all nodes it has created. Ownership cannot be transferred. The message
bus manages access rights to nodes as a set of <emphasis>handles</emphasis> held
by each peer. For each node a peer has access to, whether it is local or remote,
the message bus keeps a handle on the peer. Initially when a node is created the
node owner is the only peer with a handle to the newly created node. Handles are
local to each peer, but can be transmitted as auxiliary data with any message,
effectively allocating a new handle to the same node in the destination peer.
This works transitively, and each peer that holds a handle can pass it on
further, or deliberately drop it. As long as a peer has a handle to a node it
can send messages to it. However, a node owner can, at any time, decide to
destroy a node. This causes all further message transactions to this node to
fail, although messages that have already been queued for the node are still
delivered. When a node is destroyed, all peers that hold handles to the node are
notified of the destruction. Moreover, if the owner of a node that has been
destroyed releases all its handles to the node, no further messages or
notifications destined for the node are delivered.
      </para>
      <para>
Handles are the only way to refer to both local and remote nodes. For each
handle allocated on a peer, a 64-bit ID is assigned to identify that particular
handle on that particular peer. The ID is only valid locally on that peer, it
cannot be used by remote peers to address the handle (in other words, the ID
namespace is tied to each peer and does not define global entities). When
creating a new node, userspace freely selects the ID except that the
<constant>BUS1_HANDLE_FLAG_MANAGED</constant> bit must be cleared, and when
receiving a handle from a remote peer the kernel assigns the ID, which always
has the <constant>BUS1_HANDLE_FLAG_MANAGED</constant> set. Additionally, the
<constant>BUS1_HANDLE_FLAG_REMOTE</constant> flag tells whether a specific ID
refers to a remote handle (if set), or to an owner handle (if unset). An ID
assigned by the kernel is never reused, even after a handle has been dropped.
The kernel keeps a user-reference count for each handle. Every time a handle is
exposed to a peer, the user-reference count of that handle is incremented by
one. This is never done asynchronously, but only synchronously when an ioctl is
called by the holding peer. Therefore, a peer can reliable deduce the current
user-reference count of all its handles, regardless of any ongoing message
transaction. References can be explicitly dropped by a peer. Once the counter of
a handle hits zero, it is destroyed, its ID becomes invalid, and if it was
assigned by the kernel, it will not be reused. Note that a peer can never have
multiple different handles to the same node, rather the kernel always coalesces
them into a single handle, using the user-reference counter to track it.
However, if a handle is fully released, but the peer later acquires a handle to
the same remote node again, its ID will be different, as IDs are never reused.
      </para>
      <para>
New nodes are allocated on-demand by passing the desired ID to the kernel in any
ioctl that accepts a handle ID. When allocating a new node, the node owner
implicitly also gets a handle to that node. As long as the node is valid, the
kernel will pin a single user-reference to the owner's handle. This guarantees
that a node owner always retains access to their node, until they explicitly
destroy it (which will make it possible for userspace to release the handle like
any other). Once all the handles to a local node have been released, no more
messages destined for the node will be received. Otherwise, a handle to a local
node behaves just like any other handle, that is, user-references are acquired
and released according to its use. However, whenever the overall sum of all
user-references on all handles to a node drops to one (which implies that only
the pinned reference of the owner is left), a release-notification is queued on
the node owner. If the counter is incremented again, any such notification is
dropped, if not already dequeued.
      </para>
    </refsect2>

    <refsect2>
      <title>Message Transactions</title>
      <para>
A message transaction atomically transfers a message to any number of
destinations. Unless requested otherwise, the message transaction fully succeeds
or fully fails.
      </para>
      <para>
To receive message payloads, each peer has an associated shmem-backed
<emphasis>pool</emphasis> which may be mapped read-only by the receiving peer.
The kernel copies the message payload directly from the sending peer to each of
the receivers' pool without an intermediary kernel buffer. The pool is divided
into <emphasis>slices</emphasis> to hold each message. When a message is
received, its <emphasis>offset</emphasis> into the pool in bytes is returned to
userspace, and userspace has to explicitly release the slice once it has
finished with it.
      </para>
    </refsect2>

    <refsect2>
      <title>Seed Message</title>
      <para>
Every peer may pin a special <emphasis>seed</emphasis> message. Only the peer
itself may set and retrieve the seed, and at most one seed message may be pinned
at any given time. The seed typically describes the peer itself and pins any
nodes and handles necessary to bootstrap the peer.
      </para>
    </refsect2>

    <refsect2>
      <title>Resource quotas</title>
      <para>
Each user has a fixed amount of available resources. The limits are static, but
may be overridden by module parameters. Limits are placed on the amount of
memory a user's pools may consume, the number of handles a user may hold and,
the number of inflight messages that may be destined for a user and the number
of file descriptors that may be inflight to a user. All inflight resources are
accounted on the receiving peer.
      </para>
      <para>
As resources are accounted on the receiver, a quota mechanism is in place in
order to avoid intentional or unintentional resource exhaustion by a malicious
or broken sending user. At the time of a message transaction, the sending user
may consume in total (including what is consumed by previous transactions) half
of the total resources of the receiving user that have not been consumed by
another user. When a message is dequeued its resource consumption is deaccounted
from the sending users quota.
      </para>
      <para>
If a receiving peer does not dequeue any of its incoming messages it would be
possible for a users quota to be fully consumed by one peer, making it
impossible to communicate with other functioning peers owned by the same user. A
second quota is therefore enforced per-peer, enforcing that at the time of a
message transaction the receiving peer may in total consume (including what
is consumed by previous transactions) half of the total resources available to
the sending user that have not been consumed by another peer.
      </para>
    </refsect2>

    <refsect2>
      <title>Global Ordering</title>
      <para>
Despite there being no global synchronization, all events on the bus, such as
sending or receiving of messages, release of handles or destruction of nodes,
behave as if they were globally ordered. That is, for any two events it is
always possible to consider one to have happened before the other in such a way
that it is consistent with all the effects observed on the bus.
      </para>
      <para>
For instance, if two events occur on one peer (say the sending of a message,
and the destruction of a node), and they are observed on another peer (by
receiving the message and receiving a destruction notification for the node), we
are guaranteed that the order the events occurred in and the order they were
observed in is the same.
      </para>
      <para>
One could consider a further example involving three peers, if a message is sent
from one peer to two others, and after receiving the message the first recipient
sends a further message to the second recipient, it is guaranteed that the
original message is received before the subsequent one.
      </para>
      <para>
This principle of causality is also respected in the presence of side-channel
communication. That is, if one event may have triggered another, even if on
different, disconnected, peers, we are guaranteed that the events are ordered
accordingly. To be precise, if one event (such as receiving a message) completed
before another (such as sending a message) was started, then they are ordered
accordingly.
      </para>
      <para>
Also in the case where there can be no causal relationship, we are guaranteed a
total order. In case two events happened concurrently, there can never be any
inconsistency in which occurred before the other. By way of example, consider
two peers sending one message each to two different peers, we are guaranteed
that both the recipient peers receive the two messages in the same order, even
though the order may be arbitrary.
      </para>
    </refsect2>

    <refsect2>
      <title>Operating on a bus1 file descriptor</title>
      <para>
The bus1 peer file descriptor supports the following operations:
      </para>
      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry> <!-- FOPS OPEN -->
          <term>
            <citerefentry>
              <refentrytitle>open</refentrytitle>
              <manvolnum>2</manvolnum>
            </citerefentry>
          </term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
A call to
<citerefentry>
  <refentrytitle>open</refentrytitle><manvolnum>2</manvolnum>
</citerefentry>
on the bus1 character device (usually <filename>/dev/bus1</filename>) creates a
new peer context identified by the returned file descriptor.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry> <!-- FOPS OPEN -->

        <varlistentry> <!-- FOPS POLL -->
          <term>
            <citerefentry>
              <refentrytitle>poll</refentrytitle>
              <manvolnum>2</manvolnum>
            </citerefentry>
          </term>
          <term>
            <citerefentry>
              <refentrytitle>select</refentrytitle>
              <manvolnum>2</manvolnum>
            </citerefentry>
          </term>
          <term>(and similar)</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
The file descriptor supports
<citerefentry>
  <refentrytitle>poll</refentrytitle><manvolnum>2</manvolnum>
</citerefentry>
(and analogously
<citerefentry>
  <refentrytitle>epoll</refentrytitle><manvolnum>7</manvolnum>
</citerefentry>) and
<citerefentry>
  <refentrytitle>select</refentrytitle><manvolnum>2</manvolnum>
</citerefentry>, as follows:
            </para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>
The file descriptor is readable (the <varname>readfds</varname> argument of
<citerefentry>
  <refentrytitle>select</refentrytitle><manvolnum>2</manvolnum>
</citerefentry>;
the <constant>POLLIN</constant> flag of
<citerefentry>
  <refentrytitle>poll</refentrytitle><manvolnum>2</manvolnum>
</citerefentry>)
if one or more messages are ready to be dequeued.
                </para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>
The file descriptor is writable (the <varname>writefds</varname> argument of
<citerefentry>
  <refentrytitle>select</refentrytitle><manvolnum>2</manvolnum>
</citerefentry>;
the <constant>POLLOUT</constant> flag of
<citerefentry>
  <refentrytitle>poll</refentrytitle><manvolnum>2</manvolnum>
</citerefentry>)
if the peer has not been shut down, yet (i.e., the peer can be used to send
messages).
                </para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>
The file descriptor signals a hang-up (overloaded on the
<varname>readfds</varname> argument of
<citerefentry>
  <refentrytitle>select</refentrytitle><manvolnum>2</manvolnum>
</citerefentry>;
the <constant>POLLHUP</constant> flag of
<citerefentry>
  <refentrytitle>poll</refentrytitle><manvolnum>2</manvolnum>
</citerefentry>)
if the peer has been shut down.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>

            <para>
The bus1 peer file descriptor also supports the other file descriptor
multiplexing APIs:
<citerefentry>
  <refentrytitle>pselect</refentrytitle><manvolnum>2</manvolnum>
</citerefentry>, and
<citerefentry>
  <refentrytitle>ppoll</refentrytitle><manvolnum>2</manvolnum>
</citerefentry>.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry> <!-- FOPS POLL -->

        <varlistentry> <!-- FOPS MMAP -->
          <term>
            <citerefentry>
              <refentrytitle>mmap</refentrytitle>
              <manvolnum>2</manvolnum>
            </citerefentry>
          </term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
A call to
<citerefentry>
  <refentrytitle>mmap</refentrytitle><manvolnum>2</manvolnum>
</citerefentry>
installs a memory mapping to the message pool of the peer into the caller's
address-space. No writable mappings are allowed. Furthermore, the pool has no
fixed size, but grows dynamically with the demands of the peer.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry> <!-- FOPS MMAP -->

        <varlistentry> <!-- FOPS IOCTL -->
          <term>
            <citerefentry>
              <refentrytitle>ioctl</refentrytitle>
              <manvolnum>2</manvolnum>
            </citerefentry>
          </term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
The following bus1-specific commands are supported:
            </para>
            <variablelist>
              <varlistentry>
                <term><constant>BUS1_CMD_PEER_DISCONNECT</constant></term>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
This argument disconnects a peer and does not take an argument. All slices,
handles, nodes and queued messages are released and destroyed and all future
operations on the peer will fail with <constant>-ESHUTDOWN</constant>.
                  </para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term><constant>BUS1_CMD_PEER_QUERY</constant></term>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
This command queries the state of a peer context. It takes the following
structure as argument:
<programlisting>
struct bus1_cmd_peer_reset {
        __u64 flags;
        __u64 peer_flags;
        __u64 max_slices;
        __u64 max_handles;
        __u64 max_inflight_bytes;
        __u64 max_inflight_fds;
};
</programlisting>
<varname>flags</varname> must always be set to 0. The state as set via
<constant>BUS1_CMD_PEER_RESET</constant>, or the default state if it was never
reset, is returned.
                  </para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term><constant>BUS1_CMD_PEER_RESET</constant></term>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
This command resets a peer context. It takes the following structure as
argument:
<programlisting>
struct bus1_cmd_peer_reset {
        __u64 flags;
        __u64 peer_flags;
        __u64 max_slices;
        __u64 max_handles;
        __u64 max_inflight_bytes;
        __u64 max_inflight_fds;
};
</programlisting>
<varname>peer_flags</varname> must always be set to -1.
<varname>max_slices</varname>, <varname>max_handles</varname>,
<varname>max_inflight_bytes</varname>, and <varname>max_inflight_fds</varname>
are the resource limits for this peer. Note that these are simply max values,
the resource usage is also limited per user.
                  </para>
                  <para>
If <varname>flags</varname> has
<constant>BUS1_CMD_PEER_RESET_FLAG_FLUSH_SEED</constant> set, the seed message
is dropped, and if <constant>BUS1_CMD_PEER_RESET_FLAG_FLUSH</constant> is set,
all slices and handles are released, all messages are dropped from the queue and
all nodes that are not pinned by the seed message are destroyed.
                  </para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term><constant>BUS1_CMD_HANDLE_TRANSFER</constant></term>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
This command transfers a handle from one peer context to another. It takes the
following structure as argument:
<programlisting>
struct bus1_cmd_handle_transfer {
        __u64 flags;
        __u64 src_handle;
        __u64 dst_fd;
        __u64 dst_handle;
};
</programlisting>
<varname>flags</varname> must always be set to 0, <varname>src_handle</varname>
is the handle ID of the handle being transferred in the source context,
<varname>dst_fd</varname> is the bus1 file descriptor representing the
destination peer context and <varname>dst_handle</varname> must be
<constant>BUS1_HANDLE_INVALID</constant> and is set to the new handle ID in the
destination context on return.
                  </para>
                  <para>
If <varname>dst_fd</varname> is set to <constant>-1</constant> the source
context is also used as the destination.
                  </para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term><constant>BUS1_CMD_HANDLE_RELEASE</constant></term>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
This command releases one user reference to a handle. It takes a handle ID as
argument.
                  </para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term><constant>BUS1_CMD_NODE_DESTROY</constant></term>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
This command destroys a set of nodes. It takes the following structure as
argument:
<programlisting>
struct bus1_cmd_node_destroy {
        __u64 flags;
        __u64 ptr_nodes;
        __u64 n_nodes;
};
</programlisting>
<varname>flags</varname> must always be set to 0, <varname>ptr_nodes</varname>
must be a pointer to an array of handle IDs of owner handles of local nodes, and
<varname>n_nodes</varname> must be the size of the array.
                  </para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term><constant>BUS1_CMD_SLICE_RELEASE</constant></term>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
This command releases one slice from the local pool. It takes a pool offset to
the start of the slice to be released.
                  </para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term><constant>BUS1_CMD_SEND</constant></term>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
This command sends a message. It takes the following structure as argument:
<programlisting>
struct bus1_cmd_send {
        __u64 flags;
        __u64 ptr_destinations;
        __u64 ptr_errors;
        __u64 n_destinations;
        __u64 ptr_vecs;
        __u64 n_vecs;
        __u64 ptr_handles;
        __u64 n_handles;
        __u64 ptr_fds;
        __u64 n_fds;
};
</programlisting>
                  </para>
                  <para>
<varname>flags</varname> may be set to at most one of
<constant>BUS1_SEND_FLAG_CONTINUE</constant> and
<constant>BUS1_SEND_FLAG_SEED</constant>. If
<constant>BUS1_SEND_FLAG_CONTINUE</constant> is set any messages that cannot
be delivered due to errors on the remote peer do not make the whole transaction
fail, but merely set the corresponding error code in the error code array
respectively. If <constant>BUS1_SEND_FLAG_SEED</constant> is set the message
replaces the seed message on the local peer. In this case,
<varname>n_destinations</varname> must be 0.
                  </para>
                  <para>
<varname>ptr_destinations</varname> is a pointer to an array of handle IDs,
<varname>ptr_errors</varname> is a pointer to an array of corresponding
errno codes, and <varname>n_destinations</varname> is the length of the arrays.
The message being sent is delivered to the peer context owning the nodes pointed
to by each of the handles in the array.
                  </para>
                  <para>
<varname>ptr_vecs</varname> is a pointer to an array of iovecs and
<varname>n_vecs</varname> is the length of the array. The iovecs represent the
payload of the message which is delivered to each destination.
                  </para>
                  <para>
<varname>ptr_handles</varname> is a pointer to an array of handle IDs and
<varname>n_handles</varname> is the length of the array. Each of the handles in
this array is installed in each destination peer context at receive time. If the
underlying node has been destroyed at the time the message is delivered (the
message would be ordered after the node's destruction notification) then
<constant>BUS1_HANDLE_INVALID</constant> will be delivered instead.
                  </para>
                  <para>
<varname>ptr_fds</varname> is a pointer to an integer array of file descriptors
and <varname>n_fds</varname> is the length of the array. If requested, each of
the file descriptors in this array is installed in the destination peer context
at receive time (see below). bus1 or
<citerefentry>
  <refentrytitle>unix</refentrytitle><manvolnum>7</manvolnum>
</citerefentry>
domain socket file descriptors may not be transferred in this way.
                  </para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term><constant>BUS1_CMD_RECV</constant></term>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
This command receives a message. It takes the following structure as argument:
<programlisting>
struct bus1_cmd_recv {
        __u64 flags;
        __u64 max_offset;
        struct {
                __u64 type;
                __u64 flags;
                __u64 destination;
                __u64 offset;
                __u64 n_bytes;
                __u64 n_handles;
                __u64 n_fds;
        } msg;
};
</programlisting>
If <constant>BUS1_RECV_FLAG_SEED</constant> is set in <varname>flags</varname>,
the peer's seed is received rather than a message from the queue. If
<constant>BUS1_RECV_FLAG_INSTALL_FDS</constant> is set, the file descriptors
attached to the received message are installed in the receiving process.
                  </para>
                  <para>
<varname>max_offset</varname> indicates the maximum offset into the pool the
receiving peer is able to read. If a message slice would exceed this offset
the call would fail with <constant>-ERANGE</constant>.
                  </para>
                  <para>
<varname>msg.type</varname> indicates the type of message.
<constant>BUS1_MSG_NONE</constant> is never returned.
<constant>BUS1_MSG_DATA</constant> indicates a regular message sent from another
peer, possibly containing a payload, as well as attached handles and
filedescriptors. <constant>BUS1_MSG_NODE_DESTROY</constant> indicates that the
node referenced by the handle in <varname>msg.destination</varname> was
destroyed by its owner. <constant>BUS1_MSG_NODE_RELEASE</constant> indicates
that all the references to handles referencing the node in
<varname>msg.destination</varname> have been released.
                  </para>
                  <para>
<varname>msg.flags</varname> indicates additional flags of the message.
<constant>BUS1_MSG_FLAG_CONTINUE</constant> indicates that there are more
messages queued which belong to the same message transaction.
                  </para>
                  <para>
<varname>msg.destination</varname> is the ID of the destination node or handle
of the message.
                  </para>
                  <para>
<varname>msg.offset</varname> is the offset, in bytes, into the pool of the
payload and <varname>msg.n_bytes</varname> is its length.
                  </para>
                  <para>
<varname>msg.n_handles</varname> is the number of handles attached to the
message. The handle IDs are stored in the pool following the payload (and
possibly padding to make the array 8-byte aligned).
                  </para>
                  <para>
<varname>msg.n_fds</varname> is the number of handles attached to the
message, or 0 if <constant>BUS1_RECV_FLAG_INSTALL_FDS</constant> was not set.
The file descriptor numbers are stored in the pool following the handle array
(and possibly padding to make the array 8-byte aligned).
                  </para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry> <!-- FOPS IOCTL -->

        <varlistentry> <!-- FOPS CLOSE -->
          <term>
            <citerefentry>
              <refentrytitle>close</refentrytitle>
              <manvolnum>2</manvolnum>
            </citerefentry>
          </term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
A call to
<citerefentry>
  <refentrytitle>close</refentrytitle><manvolnum>2</manvolnum>
</citerefentry>
releases the passed file descriptor. When all file descriptors associated with
the same peer context have been closed, the peer is shut down. This destroys all
nodes of that peer, releases all handles, flushes its queue and pool, and
deallocates all related resources. Messages that have been sent by the peer and
are still queued on destination queues are unaffected by this.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry> <!-- FOPS CLOSE -->
      </variablelist>
    </refsect2>
  </refsect1> <!-- DESCRIPTION -->

  <refsect1> <!-- RETURN VALUE -->
    <title>Return value</title>
    <para>
All bus1 operations return zero on success. On failure, a negative error code is
returned.
    </para>
  </refsect1> <!-- RETURN VALUE -->

  <refsect1> <!-- ERRORS -->
    <title>Errors</title>
    <para>
These are all standard errors generated by the bus layer. See the description
of each ioctl for details on their occurrence.
    </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><constant>EAGAIN</constant></term>
        <listitem><para>
No messages ready to be read.
        </para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term><constant>EBADF</constant></term>
        <listitem><para>
Invalid file descriptor.
        </para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term><constant>EDQUOT</constant></term>
        <listitem><para>
Resource quota exceeded.
        </para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term><constant>EFAULT</constant></term>
        <listitem><para>
Cannot read, or write, ioctl parameters.
        </para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term><constant>EHOSTUNREACH</constant></term>
        <listitem><para>
The destination object is no longer available.
        </para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term><constant>EINVAL</constant></term>
        <listitem><para>
Invalid ioctl parameters.
        </para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term><constant>EMSGSIZE</constant></term>
        <listitem><para>
The message to be sent exceeds its allowed resource limits.
        </para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term><constant>ENOMEM</constant></term>
        <listitem><para>
Out of kernel memory.
        </para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term><constant>ENOTTY</constant></term>
        <listitem><para>
Unknown ioctl.
        </para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term><constant>ENXIO</constant></term>
        <listitem><para>
Unknown object.
        </para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term><constant>EOPNOTSUPP</constant></term>
        <listitem><para>
Operation not supported.
        </para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term><constant>EPERM</constant></term>
        <listitem><para>
Permission denied.
        </para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term><constant>ERANGE</constant></term>
        <listitem><para>
The message to be received would exceed the maximal offset.
        </para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term><constant>ESHUTDOWN</constant></term>
        <listitem><para>
Local peer was already disconnected.
        </para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </refsect1> <!-- ERRORS -->

</refentry>
